JACK: Torchwood.
Outside the government,
beyond the police.
Fighting for the future
on behalf of the human race.
The 2 1 st century
is when everything changes
and Torchwood is ready.
(MOBILE PHON E BEEPING)
(CH UCKLES)
Cheeky bugger.
(WIN D HOWLING)
AN DY: Jonah Bevan,
born 15th of February, 1993.
Son of N ikki Bevan and Paul Millet.
14 Cliffs Rise, Penarth.
Disappeared walking home
from football practise.
Been missing now
for seven months and eleven days.
No body, no sighting since that night.
Disappeared right where we're standing.
Mmm-hmm.
Which is where we found this.
He sent a text to his mum,
she was looking out the window
and they waved to each other.
-She's certain everywhere was deserted.
-What about the investigation?
Usual procedures, searched the home,
checked the computer,
spoken to all known friends
and relatives, made publicity appeals.
But no significant leads...
Look, sorry,
-is this beneath you now?
-No.
Then what's with the attitude?
You got a face like a slapped arse.
I'm waiting for you to tell me
where you were.
-Where I was when?
-At the wedding.
I rang you, I had to work.
Temple changed the rota
at the last minute.
-You know how it is.
-I checked the duty logs,
you weren't working,
you had three days off.
-What, are you spying on me now?
-I thought we were mates.
-And you just don't turn up?
-Just thought...
Being as Rhys has got
a problem with me...
Rhys thinks you're great.
It's you who has a problem with him.
Ever since I've known you, you've made
sarky comments about his weight.
He could stand to lose
a couple of pounds.
Let it go! Let it go.
Yeah, well, I can't. All right?
I don't want to sit there and watch you
pledge your stupid life to him.
I've got better things to do
of a Saturday. Happy now?
-Oh, Andy!
-Get off.
I thought we'd been through all this,
you're a lovely fella and stuff.
I'm not like a bloody tap,
I can't just switch it off.
But this was like what, three years ago?
I mean, look, I didn't know...
I didn't realise you still had feelings.
I don't, all right? I just had a moment.
-Don't flatter yourself.
- (CH UCKLING) Okay.
-If you want to talk about it...
-I want to talk about this kid.
-Jonah.
-Teenagers go missing all the time.
I mean, why is this one so special?
I was the first one here.
I sat with his mum all night
and all the next day.
And every time I tell her we got
nothing new, I see a bit of her die.
Anything strange about the case?
Like you don't know.
(WOMAN CHATTERING ON POLICE RADIO)
-What... What just happened?
-Exactly.
AN DY: The camera records one frame
every six seconds.
He could've done a lot in six seconds,
jumped over the side, hidden somewhere.
No, he's looking at something.
Look, something is glowing
just out of the camera's line of sight,
like a flare.
It's not there the previous frame
or the next.
Could be one of the lights
on the barrage.
All right, stop lying.
You know what happened here,
-why aren't you telling me?
-What are you talking about, Andy?
Right. Forty-five minutes later...
What's your mate Mulder doing there?
GWEN : Jack?
No recognisable rift activity
around the barrage on that date.
-What about if you tried...
-I ran checks for three months
either side then extended the radius
by a mile and checked again.
-Still nothing.
-Okay. Thanks.
-When did you say this was?
-It was about seven months back.
Any reason you'd be
on the barrage that night?
They have this cute little coffee shack,
I sometimes stop by there.
A boy went missing
just under an hour
before you were there.
-Okay.
-Jonah Bevan, 15 years old.
I thought maybe you were out there
because of him.
Maybe if we'd registered rift activity.
No, I just checked with Tosh,
it was all clear.
Sorry, can't help.
-Want me to look into it for you?
-No, it's fine.
-So it was just a coincidence, then?
-I guess so.
Gotta run. Weevil hunting with Ianto.
(POLICE SIREN WAILING)
WOMAN : Ah-choo.
(MAN CH UCKLING)
AN DY: Oh, I like that.
(PEOPLE CHATTERING)
So, you're covering it up, then?
Jack said it was a coincidence.
I can't help.
Thanks a lot.
Should've known. Bloody Torchwood.
Fob me off, why don't you?
No, if there was something going on,
I would tell you.
Do you know what's happened
to you, Gwen? You've got hard.
Yeah? Well, maybe I've had to.
You used to care.
You used to be bothered about people.
Don't matter who they were
or what they did.
And now you sit here
talking about coincidence,
like people go missing all the time,
like it's a fact of life.
The old Gwen would've been up there
to see N ikki Bevan in a flash.
You're one of them now, aren't you?
Too busy to bother
with one missing child.
What is it? Not major enough for you?
Not spooky enough?
Sorry to bother you.
(DOOR BELL RINGING)
N ikki Bevan? Gwen Cooper.
I'm working with the police
on Jonah's disappearance.
-Andy said you might be round.
-Oh, he did, did he?
Reckons you've got
a different area of expertise.
What is it, forensics?
-I'm just a fresh eye.
-Oh, sorry about the mess.
Wow, film fan, are you?
-Crowds.
-Sorry?
It's all crowd footage,
ever since he went.
Football matches, concerts, festivals.
Anywhere there's a crowd, I record it.
Go through it frame by frame,
checking every face.
Sometimes I think it's him.
But the picture's so grainy,
I spend hours
looking at one corner of the screen.
But then the next day,
I check again and it's not.
It's the hope that's killing me.
-Even if you saw him, what would you do?
-Find someone that was with him.
If I could just let him know I saw him.
He's got to be out there somewhere.
Do you think I'm mad?
No, I think you'd make
a great police woman.
This room's as he left it?
I sleep in here some nights.
Bury my head in the pillow.
It still smells of him.
Except the more I do it,
the more it smells like me.
I keep his diary for him.
I sit in here and I imagine I'm him.
-What do you think I did wrong?
-Sorry?
Maybe I was to nosy.
Or not interested enough.
Maybe he felt unloved.
All I've got is questions.
-What about Jonah's dad?
-We were only together about six weeks.
I thought when he first went missing
and he was all over the telly
that his dad might get in touch, but no.
Still manages to disappoint.
Oh, hang on.
Andy tried to find me a support group,
but there weren't any.
So I thought I'd set one up myself.
-It's our first meeting, will you come?
-Oh, I don't know.
Andy'll be there. And I'm gonna do food.
Oh, come on, I don't want to be
sat there on my own.
I'll try. I've got to go.
-I'm sorry, I know I'm late.
-Three hours!
It was a work thing,
time just got away from me.
Ooh, wine. We can do it
another time, though, yeah?
This is the fourth another time, Gwen.
-You said you'd cook.
-Did I?
-When are we going to have this talk?
-Let's do it now.
Come on, now is good. I'm ready.
-Babies. Now.
-Really?
-Do you think I've changed?
-Eh?
Since I joined Torchwood,
am I different?
-Why?
-It's just something Andy said.
Okay, let me just tell you
this one thing, okay?
-Okay, go on.
-He still fancies me.
Don't laugh, Rhys. That's why
he didn't come to the wedding.
-Bloody hell, poor sod.
-Oi !
I'm a very sexy lady
and you are a very lucky man.
Just remember that, okay?
We're not going
to talk about kids tonight, are we?
We could do some practising.
(BOTH CH UCKLING)
-GWEN : Tell me you love me.
-Give me the toast.
Oh, come on, tell me you love me first.
-Give me the toast!
-Tell me you love me.
(MOBILE PHON E RINGING)
-Gwen.
-H i, Tosh.
I've dug up some new data
on that night at the barrage.
I think you might want
to take a look at it.
I'll be right there.
-Deserting me, are you?
-Yep.
-GWEN : Ugh, crumbs.
-Oi !
Hey, what've you got?
It's barely a blip on the system.
So insignificant I've been ignoring it.
But when I looked closer...
This is what we recognise
as standard rift activity.
But what I discovered is
a negative rift spike
that occurred at the time
you're querying.
Now, we've always assumed
that these readings
were residual rift flares.
Like an aftershock.
But because this one coincided
with Jonah's disappearance,
I think we've been misinterpreting.
-Okay, so...
-So, we've always believed
that things can only come
through the rift one way.
What if we're wrong? What if the rift
doesn't just leave stuff behind?
What if it also takes?
-Who else have you told about this?
-No one.
I called you as soon as I realised.
But it could be a coincidence
or an anomaly.
I can't be sure unless I can
cross-reference it with other examples.
Tosh, can we keep this to ourselves?
There's something I have to do.
Whatever you think is best.
Thank you so much,
you're such a sweetheart.
-You're looking into it, then?
-Still the same old me.
Thank you.
Yeah, well, I don't know why I bother,
you're so rude.
How's Rhys? Other than hungry.
-Oh. It's you two.
-AN DY: Oh, that's nice.
I thought there'd be more here by now.
-It's going to just be me, isn't it?
-I'm sure it won't. People will come.
Yeah, yeah, you know,
"If you build it, they will come."
Field ofDreams. No? Just me, then.
Anyway, sit down.
It is going to be just us, isn't it?
(KNOCKING)
-H i, we're looking for N ikki.
-Yeah, that's me. Come in.
It's brilliant you found us.
There's food there, drinks,
so help yourself.
-Is this missing persons?
-Yeah, come in. Do you want a drink?
Bloody hell, how many of them are there?
-You okay?
-It's getting a bit too much now.
-I don't know what you mean.
-I said I'd help you look for one lad.
What about all those people in there,
what, 40, 50?
Am I supposed to help all them, too?
Of course not. Just focus on Jonah.
The rest aren't
part of this investigation.
But they are. Of course they are.
No, no they're not.
Find a pattern. Find out what happens,
we might find Jonah.
-What?
-Brilliant.
You're brilliant. I've got to go.
-Where you going?
-Cross-referencing !
Cross...
Cross-referencing?
You said we needed more data
to be certain the rift takes people.
List of all missing persons
in Cardiff over the last 10 years.
I'll deal with the personal details
and I'm sending you dates, locations
and approximate times they went missing.
And you want me to check the dates
they went missing
against negative rift spikes?
Yes, I do, and I'll dig out
any CCTV footage.
What about Jack?
Do we tell him what we're doing?
When we're sure.
Tosh, if we can prove you were right,
we can start looking for the people
who've been taken.
Maybe even try and stop it
from happening.
Oh, my God. There are really this many?
Now we tell Jack.
Cardiff has an epidemic
of missing persons,
totally out of kilter
with any other comparable city.
And it's all down to the rift.
IANTO: Are you sure they aren't just
normal missing persons?
People do go missing for other reasons.
No, Toshiko crossed-referenced
the locations with the rift spikes.
The people we've identified here
are definitely the victims of the rift.
What do we think happens to them?
Scattered through time
and space, I guess.
Cheery thought. Thank you.
This is good work.
But I don't know what you want us to do.
We find a way to prevent it.
Toshiko, can we predict
when the spikes are going to happen?
No. And they're gone
in a matter of seconds.
-Then I don't know how we combat them.
-Jack, we have a duty here.
These people are victims of the rift.
-If they'd been attacked by a Weevil...
-Weevil's we can catch.
If they're victims, we fix their wounds.
But this, we don't know
when it's going to happen.
We don't know where they end up.
Seriously, Gwen, practically,
tell me what we should do.
We help those left behind.
Why not?
(JACK SIGHING)
-It's nothing to do with us. Move on.
-Jack, you should see these people.
-Some things we can't fix.
-So we don't even try?
Look, Jack's right.
They need counselling, support.
-That is not us.
-Ah, okay, is that what you all think?
We are the only ones who know the truth.
We can help them.
We don't have to be this hard.
-It's not a badge of honour, Jack.
-Close this down.
Jack!
I'll talk to him.
So, is that it, then?
We just sweep it under the carpet?
God grant me the serenity to accept
the things I cannot change.
Oh, bollocks to serenity!
For a lovely girl,
you've got a very dirty mouth.
-Yes.
-I'm with Jack.
-We did our best.
-Thanks, Tosh.
So on the one hand,
you've got blokes like Mo,
who swears it's the best thing
he's done in his life.
And then on the other,
you've got Big Dave,
who says he feels like his life's ended
and how he's a second class citizen
in his own house.
Although to be fair,
he said his life had ended
when Susy made him ditch the bike.
Will you just stop wittering?
Thank you. God !
It's not wittering. It's talking.
We're supposed to be talking.
I've been trying to talk to you
for a week,
but for some reason you don't want to.
Oh, wake up, Rhys. What's the point?
We don't need a talk.
It takes two seconds' thought.
How are we supposed to have kids
with my job?
Torchwood does not do maternity leave.
"Oh, I'm sorry, Jack,
"I'd love to help out with the aliens
but I can't get a baby-sitter.
" No, no, no, I'll sort out that bomb
"once I've dropped Rhys Junior
at nursery."
Stop dancing around it,
it's a dead question.
You know, sometimes I fucking hate you !
I mean, look at you,
caught up in your little group
like nothing else matters.
Like being a hero is an end in itself.
Well, it's not.
You save this city. Well done.
You save the world. Whatever. What for?
-Sorry?
-Why are you doing it?
What are you trying to protect?
What are you fighting for?
-Because if I don't...
-Shut up, I'm talking now, right?
You do it
so people can live their lives.
And there's nothing
more important than that.
Falling in love, getting married,
buying flats, having kids or not.
But real life,
that's what you're protecting.
And if you're starting to think
that your shit
is more important than real life,
then we're not going
to last very long here, love.
I'm sorry.
-There's this thing at work...
-I don't care! I don't care!
When you're with me,
we deal with us, right? Our lives.
You got a problem at work,
you sort it at work.
Jack?
-Was there something you wanted?
-Jonah Bevan. The missing boy.
I'll make it my own special project.
My responsibility. Nothing to do with
anyone else. I'm not letting it go.
No.
-What?
-I don't know how I can be any clearer.
Oh. Well, Tosh has her projects,
so does Ianto. Why can't I?
-Leave it alone.
-I can't.
-Coming back in? Work to do.
-Yup.
-Jack, we're not finished.
-Yes, we are.
Uh...
There's a package on your desk.
(MOBILE PHON E RINGING)
-Hello?
-You still working?
-Sort of.
-Thought so.
There's a cup of tea here
with your name on it.
And you think this is going to help us
with the Jonah Bevan case?
Andy, just leave it, will you?
This is hi-tech stuff.
-Sorry, no. It's GPS.
-What?
Global Positioning System.
About as hi-tech as my mobile phone.
What you got here is a glorified map.
Ooh, X marks the spot, eh?
X being the middle of
the Bristol Channel.
Oh, no, hang on. Sorry, no.
Flat Holm Island.
Who's sending you out there, then?
That's just deserted scrubland.
Couldn't get us a refill, could you?
While you bask in
my technical brilliance?
(MOBILE PHON E RINGING)
-Hello?
-You left me that package, didn't you?
JACK: Ianto?
-I don't know what you mean.
-Ianto, what's going on?
-N ight, Gwen.
-JACK: Ianto!
Ianto, don't you...
Right. So, first thing in the morning,
we hire a boat.
Now, I know a couple of boat skippers
who owe me a favour.
So we'll head out to Flat Holm,
poke around,
see if we can sort this out.
Or even better, you get me the boat
and I'll tell you what I find.
No boat trip, no boat. I'm part of this.
-Okay.
-Brilliant.
-But you do as I say.
-Yeah, of course, yeah. Listen.
I was gonna ask...
Promise me you won't laugh.
Have you got any vacancies coming up?
You know, with Torchwood.
'Cause I was thinking,
I'm great to work with.
You know, you could tip them the wink.
Maybe, yeah.
-WOMAN : What can I get you, lads?
-Two burgers and two teas, please.
GWEN : Andy!
50 quid.
That's a bit steep, isn't it?
Offer him £35.
Gwen, I'm not being funny.
If you want to haggle, go to Morocco.
(SIGHING) All right, 50 quid.
Then open waves, here we come.
-Get us a couple of teas before we go.
-You're kidding?
You're not kidding? I don't know.
Do this for me and
I'll give you 100 quid.
Oi !
I'm sorry, Andy!
Yeah, right!
I'm sorry!
(GWEN SIGHS)
(ELECTRIC BUZZING)
(BELL BUZZING)
WOMAN ON SPEAKER: All right!
Who are you?
Torchwood.
Access code 4743 17432 .
I'm with Jack Harkness.
He's supposed to warn us about visitors.
Law unto himself, isn't he?
(DOOR OPENING)
And he knows we'll always forgive him.
(MAN SCREAMING)
ONTV: ...those that stand out
can become immediate targets...
This your first time?
We all find it difficult at first.
Are you looking for anyone
in particular?
Yes.
-How many people are down here?
-Didn't he tell you?
(MAN SOBBING)
What's that?
-Is he okay?
-We do our best to help him.
Caroline.
Sorry, but why are they...
Are you all right?
Oh, my God !
They're here.
What are you doing to them?
What's going on here? Tell me!
I'll take it from here, Helen.
-It was Ianto, wasn't it?
-What are you doing?
-I can explain.
-No, no, no, no. You stay away from me!
Gwen, let's go outside and talk.
These are the people taken by the rift.
What are they doing here?
-What have you done?
-Gwen, listen to me.
He's here.
-He's been here all along.
-It's not that simple.
-Open it.
-Gwen, before I...
Now!
(DOOR U N LOCKS)
Hello?
Jonah?
(MAN GRU NTING)
I'm looking for Jonah.
Why?
Am I in the right room?
(MAN BREATHING H EAVILY)
Yes.
I'm Jonah.
I'm sorry, I must be in the wrong room.
The Jonah Bevan I'm looking for
is 15 years old
and he went missing from the barrage.
That was me.
-Who are you?
-My name is Gwen Cooper,
and I'm with Torchwood. What...
What's happened to you?
I was walking home.
There was a light.
I woke up and the land was on fire.
There were flames for miles on end.
A man pulled me from the flames.
Took me to a building
where they tried to work on the burns.
I thought I was going to die.
I don't remember when the ground
started shaking.
And then I realised
it wasn't a building after all.
It was a rescue craft.
The last off a burning planet.
We watched the solar system
burn.
It was so beautiful.
I am so sorry for
what's happened to you.
Can I trust you to tell the truth?
Of course.
Am I really home?
Yes, you're home.
Thank you.
Jonah, I've come because
your mother is still looking for you.
-She's still alive?
-You've only been gone for seven months.
-She never stopped looking.
-I tried so hard to come home.
I was lost so long.
You're safe now. You are safe.
Can I see her? Can you bring her here?
Is that what you want?
When I took over Torchwood,
there were two just like Jonah.
Ravaged from falling through the rift.
Being kept in the vaults, neglected.
I wanted them looked after.
I set this place up.
Told the staff these were experiments
that had gone wrong.
-How many are there?
-Seventeen last count.
(GWEN EXHALES)
It's increased over the last year.
Like the rift is trying
to correct its mistakes.
But not all the missing return?
-No.
-You can't keep them hidden.
They have families who deserve to know.
Gwen, they're sick.
In ways you could never imagine.
We can't fix them.
We just care for them.
Jonah's asked me to bring N ikki here.
-No.
-She has a right to know.
-No way.
-She said not knowing is the worst part.
How are you going to tell her
her child has aged 40 years
in the last seven months?
That he's scarred,
that he cannot look after...
We don't have the right
to hide it from her.
If you tell her, you have to tell her
about the rift and Torchwood.
-Then I will.
-What if she doesn't believe you?
I have to try. We owe her the truth.
Jack, if you'd lost someone,
wouldn't you want to know?
Let me try. Please.
We got another meeting on Tuesday.
Will you come to that, or...
You're not here for small talk.
I've found Jonah.
-Is he dead?
-No.
Is he hurt?
-We're looking after him.
-Where? Can I see him?
Yes.
Sorry.
N ikki, there are things
I have to tell you first.
And all I'm asking is you trust me.
(MOBILE PHON E RINGING)
GWEN :
Andy, I know you hate me right now.
-I'm hanging up.
-No, no, no. Please don't.
It's about N ikki. I found Jonah.
-Where?
-I can't tell you that.
Oh, here we go again.
Piss off, why don't you?
I've got N ikki with me.
I've told her about Torchwood
and about what we do.
I need you to confirm to her that
I'm not mad or dangerous or a liar.
-You used me, Gwen.
-Sorry.
That's how you see me, isn't it?
Occasionally useful. Worth stringing
along in case I can ever help you.
Andy.
You'd never recommend for me
to join Torchwood, would you?
No.
Thank you.
I want to take N ikki to see Jonah.
But you've got to tell her that
she can trust me. We can fix this, Andy.
We can make it right.
(SIGHING) Put her on.
N ikki.
Andy.
Okay.
Where is he?
Remember what I said, you're not
going to recognise him at first.
-I know.
-He's aged. He's been injured...
I just want to see him.
You understand what
I've told you now, N ikki?
-He's not a child any more...
-It doesn't matter. I have to see him.
Let me see him.
Okay.
Hello?
Jonah?
Yes?
I can't see you.
Jonah?
-Mum.
-No.
-It's okay, Mum. It's me. It's okay.
-Stay away!
-Shh.
I'm sorry. I'm really, really sorry.
-What are you doing?
-Shh.
-What have you done to me?
-N ikki, I promise. This is Jonah.
That is not my son !
Get me out.
-I want to get out of here.
-Will you listen, please? This is him.
-You are sick. All of you !
-Listen to me...
Did you fix my wardrobe door?
We bought it flat-pack,
made it together.
Bottom left hinge keeps coming loose.
-You said you'd sort it.
-No.
Every evening
you'd buy a bottle of beer.
You let me sneak one sip, just the one.
Don't want to get a habit for it.
You got two alarms 'cause
you always sleep through the first.
Make him stop.
You talk about the day
when you can earn decent money
and afford yourself some decent make-up.
-I'm not hearing this.
-You won't buy me a double bed
because you don't understand
what I need it for.
-Shut up!
-And when I ask you
why you haven't got married,
you say you'll never be lonely
because I've always got you.
(SOBBING) It's me, Mum !
It's me!
Jonah?
I've been so lost.
I walked for years trying to get home.
-I'm sorry.
-Why?
That night. I was late.
I'm sorry.
(NIKKI SOBBING)
Ah, the sights I've seen, Mum.
It's fine.
-It'll take time.
-It'll be okay.
You have to leave Jonah now.
-What?
-Helen...
It's for your own benefit.
No. I'm taking him home now.
N ikki, stop for a second.
You can't just take him out of here.
I know how to look after my child.
I'll tell them he's my father.
-I can take care of him.
-We can't allow that.
He's my son ! I say what's allowed !
-Jonah?
-It's started again.
-What's happening?
-H ELEN : He's starting the downswing.
What's a downswing?
What is it? Jonah !
You've seen him in the good phase.
It gets briefer every day.
-It really might be best if you leave.
- (GRU NTING) Helen...
Oh, it's all right, sweetheart.
I'm here.
-Make it stop.
-I wish I could.
Please, it would be better
if you didn't stay.
-I'm not leaving. I'm not leaving him.
-Okay, okay.
-Then you should move away.
-Why?
Will you tell me why?
(NIKKI SCREAMING)
(GWEN GROANS)
GWEN: I'd never heard a sound like it.
This primal howl.
The scream lasts 20 hours every day.
Before the rift returned him, Jonah had
looked into the heart of a dark star.
What he'd seen had driven him mad.
They say you can visit.
Whenever you like.
When he's in a good phase.
Promise me you won't
do this to anyone else.
Before, I had the memory.
Whenever I thought of him,
I'd see him laughing with his mates,
playing football,
scoffing his breakfast.
And now I just hear that...
That terrible noise.
I thought you wanted to know
what happened to him.
I did.
I was wrong.
It was better when I didn't know.
Before you,
I had hope.
(SIGHING)
Apology, is it?
Tonight we talk about what you want.
Kids,
the future, anything you want.
You all right?
Hey, come here.
(GWEN CRYING)
I'm sorry.
You wanna sit down? Okay?
Okay.
Now then.
You tell me everything,
from the beginning.
There's this woman, N ikki.
She had a son,
Jonah.
He went missing seven months ago...
JACK: Some people believe that
in the moments before your death,
your life flashes before your eyes.
IANTO: Explosive devices.
Snap!